<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
	<title>wissel.net Usability - Productivity - Business - The web - Singapore and Twins</title>
	<link>https://wissel.net/blog/stories.rss</link>
	<description>Thoughts, Insights and Opinions of Stephan H. Wissel. Topics included: IBM Lotus Notes and Domino, IBM Websphere, other IBM Lotus stuff,  J2EE, .Net, Software Archtecture, Personcentric Development, Agile Software, SDLC, Singapore and my Twins</description>
	<language>en,de</language>
	<copyright>(C) 2003 - 2018 Stephan H. Wissel, All rights reserved</copyright>
	<pubdate>Mon, 02 Apr 2018 17:12:12 +0000</pubdate>
<item>
	<title>Salesforce one year on</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;A year ago I said &lt;a href="2017/04/goodbye-ibm-hello-salesforce.html"&gt;Good by IBM, Hello Salesforce&lt;/a&gt;. A lot has happened in the last 12 month. Salesforce is only my second salaried job, I've been running my own companies and been freelance before.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Coming from IBM, where &lt;em&gt;Resource Actions&lt;/em&gt; had efficiently killed employee engagement, Salesforce's Ohana culture was a refreshing different. It makes such a difference to work with people who are genuinely interested in your success, without exception. In summary:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;I became a &lt;a href="https://trailhead.salesforce.com/en/me/stwissel"&gt;Trailblazer Ranger&lt;/a&gt;, completing 30 trails, 206 badges and collecting 169625 points&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Passed five Salesforce certifications&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Contributed to customer success in Singapore, Australia and Korea&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Wrote 25 blog entries (Way to little, more are coming)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Moved my blog from Domino to git (more on that below)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Contributed to OpenSource on github: 
  &lt;ul&gt; 
   &lt;li&gt;Maintainer for &lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/node-red-contrib-salesforce"&gt;node-red-contrib-salesforce&lt;/a&gt;. The nodes that connect &lt;a href="https://nodered.org"&gt;NodeRED&lt;/a&gt; to Salesforce, including the support for platform events&lt;/li&gt; 
   &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/Excel2XML"&gt;Excel2XML&lt;/a&gt;: Tool that converts XLSX tables into XML, so data can be extracted in command line applications. Main purpose is to make Excel data accessible in build pipelines (e.g. sample values for tests)&lt;/li&gt; 
   &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/SpringCanvasSample"&gt;Spring Boot and Salesforce Canvas&lt;/a&gt;: Sample application that turns a Canvas POST into a JWT authentication, so classic multi pages applications can be integrated into Salesforce Canvas&lt;/li&gt; 
   &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/SampleProxy"&gt;Vert.x proxy&lt;/a&gt; Filtering proxy implemented in &lt;a href="https://vertx.io"&gt;Apache vert.x&lt;/a&gt;. It allows to front a web application and filter HTML, JSON etc. based on content and URL&lt;/li&gt; 
   &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/vertx-sfdc-platformevents"&gt;SFDC Platform Events&lt;/a&gt;: Modules for &lt;a href="https://vertx.io"&gt;Apache vert.x&lt;/a&gt; to connect to Salesforce. It includes authentication and processing of platform events. This allows for high performance multi-threaded interaction with Salesforce APIs, not limited to platform events&lt;/li&gt; 
   &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/blog-comments-public"&gt;Blog Comments&lt;/a&gt; Tool that accepts a JSON formated comment structure and creates a Bitbucket file, a commit and a pull request. Allows for a database free comment engine&lt;/li&gt; 
   &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/blogengine"&gt;BlogEngine&lt;/a&gt;: The application that powers this blog. It generates static files when commits/merges happen to my master branch on Bitbucket&lt;/li&gt; 
  &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;What a ride, onto year two!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/04/salesforce-one-year-on.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>39d80750-3568-11e8-876d-71d5cc4499a1</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-04-01 12:50</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Boolean to get major overhaul</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/George_Boole"&gt;George Boole&lt;/a&gt; didn't seem to understand his five teenage daughters, (he didn't have sons, so this is about teenagers, not daughters) otherwise his boolean logic would encompass not only &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;, but also &lt;code&gt;maybe&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;don't know&lt;/code&gt;. Luckily that omission will be addressed now.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#boolean-to-merge-with-ternary" id="boolean-to-merge-with-ternary"&gt;Boolean to merge with Ternary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quick recap&lt;/strong&gt;: a boolean value has the values &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; (usually 1), &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt; (usually 0). Ternary has 3 states, typically denoted -1, 0, 1. Not to confuse ternary with QBits which are true and false at the same time.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;To reflect the real world, where nothing is certain, and cater to teenage level developers, the ternary and boolean data types will be merged into a new type: &lt;strong&gt;RealBoolean&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Proposals are under way to incorporate RealBoolean into all major programming languages ASAP. RealBoolean will have the values &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;undecided&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;. While it is up to the programming languages how these values are represented, consensus is, that the most likely candidates are -1, 0 and 1.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#new-hardware" id="new-hardware"&gt;New hardware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Like specialized mining hardware for Crypto, RealBoolean will benefit from purpose build ternary computers. &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Setun"&gt;Early models&lt;/a&gt; had been running since 1958. Ternary computing also has arrived in &lt;a href="https://hackaday.com/2016/12/16/building-the-first-ternary-microprocessor/"&gt;micro processor architectures&lt;/a&gt;. Of course there are &lt;a href="https://www.techopedia.com/why-not-ternary-computers/2/32427"&gt;doubters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#transition-period" id="transition-period"&gt;Transition period&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Having multiple data types to express the truth might fit the political desire for &lt;em&gt;alternate facts&lt;/em&gt;, but is an unsustainable confusion in programming. Therefore the classic boolean values will become illegal April 01, 2042.&lt;br&gt; In the transition period classic booleans will be &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Duck_typing"&gt;ducktyped&lt;/a&gt; into RealBoolean whenever the values &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; are used. For boolean &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;-1&lt;/code&gt; (as some unfortunate languages use) compilers and runtimes are mandated to issue a &lt;strong&gt;warning&lt;/strong&gt; for the first 5 years, thereafter a &lt;strong&gt;stern warning&lt;/strong&gt; before they finally become illegal&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#enforcement" id="enforcement"&gt;Enforcement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;All version control repositories will be scanned (the NSA does that anyway) and offending code flagged with new issues. Binary code, not compiled from a repository, will be treated as virus, blocked and deleted. After the deadline all remaining offending code will be transpiled into COBOL - good luck with finding developers to make sense of that code thereafter&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/04/boolean-to-get-major-overhaul.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>2efe5190-3568-11e8-9f7b-dd4d46818a1f</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-04-01 12:50</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Authenticate from Salesforce to Heroku with JWT</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://heroku.com"&gt;Heroku&lt;/a&gt; PAAS is an easy and flexible way to extend Salesforce functionality.&lt;br&gt; Its easy to call out to a Heroku REST service build with a method of your choice: Java, JavaScript, Ruby etc.&lt;br&gt; The usual sticky point between two platforms is the &lt;strong&gt;identity of the caller&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;In a lot of cases the only requirement is ?a valid Salesforce user?, eventually with some additional claims added.&lt;br&gt; For this scenario a &lt;a href="https://jwt.io/"&gt;JWT&lt;/a&gt; Bearer authentication (&lt;a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7519"&gt;RFC 7519&lt;/a&gt;) is a good pick.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;When you look around, most examples revolve around a JWT token being issued after some means of authentication from the same system that was authenticated against.&lt;br&gt; This scenario is different: The Salesforce server issues the JWT token and code on Heroku validates the token as authorization.&lt;br&gt; The beauty of the approach: &lt;strong&gt;no extra calls&lt;/strong&gt; need to be made to get this working.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;What you will need:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;A valid certificate, in this case self signed is good enough (it won't be used by a browser)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://openssl.org"&gt;OpenSSL&lt;/a&gt; installed on your computer&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;A Heroku account&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#preparing-the-certificate" id="preparing-the-certificate"&gt;Preparing the certificate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;In Salesforce setup open &lt;a href="https://help.salesforce.com/articleView?id=security_keys_about.htm&amp;amp;type=5"&gt;Certificate and Key management&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt; Create or pick a key. Note down the name. For this article I will use &lt;em&gt;YourCertNameHere&lt;/em&gt;. Open the key and click on &lt;em&gt;Download Certificate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt; The cert will be downloaded in crt format. We use this file to extract the &lt;strong&gt;public&lt;/strong&gt; key that Heroku will use to verify the signature. To get the key use:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;pre class="brush: bash"&gt;openssl x509 -pubkey -noout -in YourCertNameHere.crt
&lt;/pre&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The String we need is between the BEGIN and END lines, excluding the lines. You can store it into a file or create a Heroku environment variable.&lt;br&gt; Since it is a public key, you don't need to guard it as fiercly as your private keys.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#the-apex-code" id="the-apex-code"&gt;The APEX code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Before making a call-out to Heroku, you need to componse the signed JWT token. That's done in just a few lines:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;pre class="brush: java"&gt;public static String getJWTBearer(String subject, String keyName) {
    Auth.JWT jwt = new Auth.JWT();
    jwt.setSub(subject);
    Auth.JWS myJws = new Auth.JWS(jwt, keyName);
    return myJws.getCompactSerialization();
}
&lt;/pre&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;You might opt to add additional claims beside the subject, when your use case does require that.&lt;br&gt; The header value gets added to the &lt;code&gt;Authorization&lt;/code&gt; header as &lt;code&gt;Bearer&lt;/code&gt; authorization.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#java-code" id="java-code"&gt;Java code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;I'm using the &lt;a href="https://github.com/jwtk/jjwt"&gt;jjwt&lt;/a&gt; library which is available on &lt;a href="https://search.maven.org/#artifactdetails%7Cio.jsonwebtoken%7Cjjwt%7C0.9.0%7Cjar"&gt;Maven Central&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt; It makes it simple to retrieve a claim. An expired claim or an invalid signature will throw an error, so wrap it into a try/catch.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;pre class="brush: java"&gt;import java.security.Key;
import java.security.KeyFactory;
import java.security.spec.X509EncodedKeySpec;
import java.util.Base64;

import io.jsonwebtoken.Claims;
import io.jsonwebtoken.Jwts;

public class JwtVerifier {
	public static Claims getClaims(String key, String token) throws Exception {

		byte[] byteKey = Base64.getMimeDecoder().decode(key);
		X509EncodedKeySpec X509publicKey = new X509EncodedKeySpec(byteKey);
		KeyFactory kf = KeyFactory.getInstance("RSA");
		Key realKey = kf.generatePublic(X509publicKey);
		return Jwts.parser().setSigningKey(realKey).parseClaimsJws(token).getBody();
	}
}
&lt;/pre&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The only catch in the code was the need for &lt;code&gt;MimeDecoder&lt;/code&gt; instead of a standard &lt;code&gt;Decoder&lt;/code&gt; for Base64 decoding.&lt;br&gt; The subject, typically the user, can be retrieved using &lt;code&gt;claims.getSubject()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Next stop, for another blog entry: the NodeJS equivalent.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;As usual YMMV!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/03/salesforce-heroku-jwt.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>cafb442a-6edb-4a5a-8414-1427353e25df</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-03-23 04:40</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Using LetsEncrypt certificates in your JKS</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Dealing with certificates in Java is always fun. The keystore Java uses is different from the certificate files you are used to in your web server or node.js.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Salesforce is build on Java, so we have to make peace with the Keystore. This article outlines the steps to use a LetsEncrypt certificate in a keystore. You will need:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Internet connection&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://openssl.org"&gt;OpenSSL&lt;/a&gt; installed&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Able to run the &lt;a href="https://letsencrypt.org/how-it-works/"&gt;LetsEncrypt challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Access to your DNS to add a record (for the challenge)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Java runtime installed&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Public IP address&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;For this sample I will use the Domain ???demo.example.com???&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#obtaining-a-pem-certficate-from-letsencrypt" id="obtaining-a-pem-certficate-from-letsencrypt"&gt;Obtaining a PEM certficate from LetsEncrypt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Easiest is to use the certbot utility on a Linux machine (e.g. spin up an instance on Heroku). DigitalOcean has &lt;a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-use-certbot-standalone-mode-to-retrieve-let-s-encrypt-ssl-certificates"&gt;detailed instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt; There used to be a tls-sni challenge which was marked insecure, so you want to the DNS challenge.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo certbot certonly --manual --preferred-challenges dns -d demo.example.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#convert-pem-to-pkcs12-format" id="convert-pem-to-pkcs12-format"&gt;Convert PEM to PKCS12 format&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;First concatenate all PEM files into one. Presuming you used the Letsencrypt mechanism:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo cat /etc/letsencrypt/life/demo.example.com/*.pem &amp;gt; fullcert.pem&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Then use OpenSSL to convert that into PKCS12 format. Note: if you do that on a Windows command prompt you must &lt;em&gt;run the command prompt as administrator&lt;/em&gt; otherwise you just get an error&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;openssl pkcs12 -export -out fullchain.pkcs12 -in fullchain.pem&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#prepare-a-java-jsk-keystore" id="prepare-a-java-jsk-keystore"&gt;Prepare a Java JSK keystore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;You can't just create an empty keystore, so create a new temp key and specify a new keystore, then delete that key. That gives you the &lt;a href="https://docs.oracle.com/cd/E35976_01/server.740/es_admin/src/tadm_ssl_convert_pem_to_jks.html"&gt;empty keystore&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;pre class="brush: bash"&gt;keytool -genkey -keyalg RSA -alias sfdcsec -keystore sfdcsec.ks
keytool -delete -alias sfdcsec -keystore sfdcsec.ks
&lt;/pre&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#import-pkcs12-into-jks" id="import-pkcs12-into-jks"&gt;Import pkcs12 into JKS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Almost final steps. Don't forget your passwords&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;keytool -v -importkeystore -srckeystore fullchain.pkcs12 -destkeystore sfdcsec.ks -deststoretype JKS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#adjust-alias-for-salesforce-import" id="adjust-alias-for-salesforce-import"&gt;Adjust alias for Salesforce import&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The Salesforce import utility is picky about Alias names. The previous import created the entry&lt;br&gt; &lt;code&gt;Alias name: 1&lt;/code&gt; which needs to be updated:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;keytool -keystore sfdcsec.ks -changealias -alias 1 -destalias demo_example_com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;And voilah, you have a properly signed certificate for your Salesforce instance. Downside: to be repeated every 90 days.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;As usual YMMV!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/03/letsencrypt-java-keystore.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>3f404a7d-3883-4a8a-a976-0e84417ff0d7</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-03-22 03:18</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>A filtering proxy server with vert.x</title>
	<description>&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#scenario" id="scenario"&gt;Scenario&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;You have this nice application running in your (cloud or on premises) environment and then &lt;a href="http://ec.europa.eu/justice/smedataprotect/index_en.htm"&gt;a big scare&lt;/a&gt; hits. Suddenly you need to remove or mask different streams of data depending on all sorts of conditions your legal department is 
 &lt;strike&gt;
  torturing
 &lt;/strike&gt; advising you.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Until your applications natively can do that, you might resort to a content filter that sits as a proxy between you and the application (technically it is a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reverse_proxy"&gt;reverse proxy&lt;/a&gt;, but that's fine print).&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;To explore the feasibility of such an approach I created &lt;a href="https://stwissel.github.io/SampleProxy/"&gt;SampleProxy&lt;/a&gt; based on work of &lt;a href="https://github.com/vietj/vertx-http-proxy"&gt;Julien Viet&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="http://vertx.io"&gt;vert.x&lt;/a&gt; as my runtime environment.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#requirements" id="requirements"&gt;Requirements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Needs to be a &lt;strong&gt;content filter&lt;/strong&gt;, not a URL blocker&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Need to provide functionality for practical use out-of-the-box, but needs to be extensible (configuration over code)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Need to be able to filter HTML, JSON, XML and Text. No need to filter binary formats. Contemplating about JavaScript (you could use the text filter for that)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Filter based on mime-type and URL as standard, but extensible to use &lt;strong&gt;anything&lt;/strong&gt; in the request or reply to decide what to filter&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Configurable FilterChain: a filter decides what to filter (with the mime-type as minimum condition) and hands actual filter operation to a chain of subfilters that do the actual stream manipulation&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;configurable subfilters. E.g. a filter that can remove JSON nodes from JSON data should read the qualifier from a configuration, so the same filter class can be reused for different filter purposes&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;CSS isn't on the radar yet, but contributions would be happily accepted&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#the-flow" id="the-flow"&gt;The flow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/2018/ProxyDataFlow.png" alt="Flow from browser to proxy to application and back"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#things-i-learned-along-the-way" id="things-i-learned-along-the-way"&gt;Things I learned along the way&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;There are always a few lessons to be had, here are some from this project:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;http is a chunked beast. When you send larger amount of content, probability approaches 1 that your server uses &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chunked_transfer_encoding"&gt;chunked&lt;/a&gt; - until HTTP/2 resolves us from it. A hard choice needs to be made to either use a stream based processing of a chunk (think &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simple_API_for_XML"&gt;SAX&lt;/a&gt;) or collecting the Junks to be able to process a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Document_Object_Model"&gt;DOM&lt;/a&gt;. To be fully flexible I opted for a DOM/Object based approach, but you are free to create whatever you deem necessary&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jsoup.org/"&gt;Jsoup&lt;/a&gt; is a reliable HTML parser. It supports &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/selectors-3/"&gt;CSS selectors&lt;/a&gt; that make addressing HTML elements a breeze. Solves one of the hardest problems: targeting&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Targeting JSON data is much harder that it needs to be, the very moment Arrays appear in your JSON structure. There is &lt;a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6901"&gt;RFC6901 JSON Pointer&lt;/a&gt;, but it targets exactly one element, while a typical use case would be: ?from the list (array) of discussion posts, pick the list of comments and those who have an eMail, mask them?. So I implemented 2 variations: a simple path style address &lt;code&gt;/discussion/posts/comments/email&lt;/code&gt; which automatically traverses arrays and an &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/Stwissel/900acc8ed6a46131530ab89bb70b9f9d"&gt;XPath based&lt;/a&gt; approach where I convert JSON to a strict XML syntax and back. More &lt;a href="/blog/2018/02/query-a-json-object-like-xpath.html"&gt;detail here&lt;/a&gt;, examples in a future post&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#items-on-the-todo-list" id="items-on-the-todo-list"&gt;Items on the ToDo list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Better documentation&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Code cleanup&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Tests&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Deploy to Heroku button&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;More filters&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#your-turn" id="your-turn"&gt;Your turn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Go &lt;a href="https://stwissel.github.io/SampleProxy/"&gt;check it out&lt;/a&gt; and let me know what you think! (Yeah - documentation needs some work).&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Caveat&lt;/strong&gt; (a.k.a disclaimer): this is a prototype and work in progress, YMMV!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/03/a-filtering-proxy-server-with-vertx.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>17171be0-1879-11e8-8afb-4b4609893bc5</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-03-04 03:18</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Query a JSON object like XPath in Java</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;I'm fond of &lt;a href="/blog/categories/xml.html"&gt;XML&lt;/a&gt; especially &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xslt/"&gt;XSLT&lt;/a&gt; and the related &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XPath"&gt;XPath&lt;/a&gt; query possibilities.&lt;br&gt; Moving into the wonderworld of &lt;a href="http://www.json.org/"&gt;JSON&lt;/a&gt; I'm missing those platform independent query and rendering options.&lt;br&gt; For templating &lt;a href="https://mustache.github.io/"&gt;Mustache&lt;/a&gt; comes close, especially in regards of platform support, but XPath still has to find its match in the JSON world.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The closest equivalent is &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/jsonpath"&gt;JSONPath&lt;/a&gt; (also available &lt;a href="https://github.com/json-path/JsonPath"&gt;for Java&lt;/a&gt; ) with a nice &lt;a href="http://jsonpath.com/"&gt;interactive playground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;I was looking at adopting it for one of &lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/SampleProxy"&gt;my projects&lt;/a&gt; written in &lt;a href="https://vertx.io"&gt;vert.x&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt; JSON isn't native to Java and there are several competing implementations around JSON: &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/gson"&gt;Google's GSON&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/FasterXML/jackson-docs"&gt;Jackson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt; and &lt;a href="http://vertx.io/docs/apidocs/io/vertx/core/json/JsonObject.html"&gt;vert.x core JsonObject&lt;/a&gt; (there are probably more).&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;So I was wondering: What if I could use XPath and by extension XSLT directly on JSON? The first step there would be a save way to transform JSON to XML and back.&lt;br&gt; Using vert.x &lt;a href="http://vertx.io/docs/apidocs/io/vertx/core/json/JsonObject.html"&gt;JsonObject&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://vertx.io/docs/apidocs/io/vertx/core/json/JsonArray.html"&gt;JsonArray&lt;/a&gt; as starting point,&lt;br&gt; I had the following considerations:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;I can't use XML tags to map to JSON labels, since labels can contain any character, XML tags are restricted&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;The resulting XML only needs 2 elements: Element and Array&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;An element can have a scalar value, my first test deals with strings only, or can contain another element or array&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;An array does not have a value. It can contain zero or more scalar values and/or zero or more arrays or elements&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;So I build a small prototype. A simple class that reads a json file from the command line, prints it to the console, transforms it to XML, prints it to the console, transforms it back and prints it again.&lt;br&gt; The prototype depends on vert.x core.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The result can be found &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/Stwissel/900acc8ed6a46131530ab89bb70b9f9d"&gt;in this gist&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="/blog/2018/02/query-a-json-object-like-xpath.html"&gt;read more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/02/query-a-json-object-like-xpath.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>26d44c30-1c32-11e8-975d-b5df85697815</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-02-28 03:50</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Spring Boot and Salesforce Canvas</title>
	<description>&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#the-challenge" id="the-challenge"&gt;The challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Salesforce canvas offers a capable integration point between Salesforce and external applications to surface them inside the Salesforce UI. One of the aspects is establishing identity. There are two options: OAuth and a signed request. I???m looking at the later. A signed request posts (as in HTTP POST) a digitally signed JSON request to the external application.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;When all you need is a single page, validating the request and returning the result is all that needs to be done. It becomes trickier when you want to navigate in the application and when that application runs in the cloud with multiple load balanced instances, so you might end up on a different instance mid-flight.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Most of the sample code available uses the sophisticated &lt;a href="https://github.com/forcedotcom/SalesforceCanvasJavascriptSDK"&gt;Canvas JavaScript SDK&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to focus on backend code here.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#the-project" id="the-project"&gt;The project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;All the code can be found &lt;a href="https://stwissel.github.io/SpringCanvasSample/"&gt;on Github&lt;/a&gt; including &lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/SpringCanvasSample"&gt;sources&lt;/a&gt;. Feel free to &lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/SpringCanvasSample/issues"&gt;open issues&lt;/a&gt;. To try it out you can deploy it to Heroku (button in the Readme on Github) and &lt;a href="https://developer.salesforce.com/docs/atlas.en-us.platform_connect.meta/platform_connect/quick_start_create_canvas_app.htm"&gt;configure a Canvas app&lt;/a&gt; in Salesforce. Use &lt;code&gt;https://yourappname.herokuapp.com/sfdcauth/hw&lt;/code&gt; as Canvas URL&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#the-approach" id="the-approach"&gt;The approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Build a &lt;a href="https://projects.spring.io/spring-boot/"&gt;Spring Boot&lt;/a&gt; application that provides an authentication endpoint suitable for a Canvas POST and other endpoints that only allow authenticated access. The security will be provided by &lt;a href="https://jwt.io/"&gt;Json Web Tokens&lt;/a&gt; a.k.a JWT or &lt;a href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7519"&gt;RFC 7519&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;As added challenge: The application will require standard link and form based navigation, so we can't rely on AJAX to provide additional ?stuff? into the requests from/to the server. And yes - needs to be able to run on &lt;a href="https://www.heroku.com/"&gt;Heroku&lt;/a&gt; on multiple instances (Dynos in Heroku language) without the sticky session feature switched on.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#lessons-learned" id="lessons-learned"&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://projects.spring.io/spring-boot/"&gt;Spring Boot&lt;/a&gt; performs magic. Sometimes a little too much magic&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Base64 isn't Base64. The Java8 decoder works different from the Apache Commons, so the signed checksums don't tally. Pain in the ?proverbial? to get the validation code from the SDK running&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Spring security is well thought through. I like the approach: the very moment you add it to a project, all is closed until you specifically open it&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;You can't stuff the entire JSON coming from Salesforce back into a cookie&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;JSON in Java is still a pain (Bearable with &lt;a href="https://fasterxml.github.io/jackson-databind/javadoc/2.2.0/com/fasterxml/jackson/databind/JsonNode.html"&gt;JsonNode&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;The information around custom error pages in Spring is confusing. It seems to have evolved over time and conflicting information is presented&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jwt.io/"&gt;Json Web Tokens&lt;/a&gt; (JWT) rock&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Cookies behave different in Salesforce canvas than in regular iFrames. In an iFrame http cookies are considered ?native? to their environment, in canvas they seem to run as third-party cookies (unless I miss something). Stole a few hours tracking the issue down&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.avonnicreator.com/"&gt;Avonni Creator&lt;/a&gt; is a nice tool to play with &lt;a href="https://www.lightningdesignsystem.com/"&gt;Lightning Design System&lt;/a&gt; layouts&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;As usual YMMV&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/02/spring-boot-and-salesforce-canvas.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>43366410-1621-11e8-8f58-bd9e0b89b056</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-02-20 09:34</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Running NodeRED on Heroku with Salesforce</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;I am a big fan of &lt;a href="http://nodered.org/"&gt;NodeRED&lt;/a&gt;, so I was delighted to see &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/node-red-contrib-salesforce"&gt;nodes available&lt;/a&gt; to connect to Salesforce.&lt;br&gt; Since the package was a little behind and support for platform events was still missing, I had a chat with &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/~jeffdonthemic"&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt; and we agreed that I would maintain the package moving forward.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;I updated the package dependencies to current version and made two main changes to the functionality:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;allow credentials to be read from environment variables. This allows for easy deployment to Heroku&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Support for Salesforce platform events&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Deployment to &lt;a href="https://www.heroku.com/apps"&gt;Heroku&lt;/a&gt; is a breeze, but requires a few steps that I document here.&lt;br&gt; The instructions require a basic understanding how Heroku works, so you might want to check out a &lt;a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/start"&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt; first. There are some challenges to overcome:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;I want to be able to test local and on the server&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Storage on Heroku is ephemeral. Any changes written to the server's file system get reset on restart&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Deployment should happen via version control&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#prerequisites" id="prerequisites"&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Current version of &lt;a href="https://nodejs.org/"&gt;NodeJS&lt;/a&gt; installed (I usually stick to the LTS version)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;GIT client installed (or GIT as part of your favorite IDE)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://devcenter.heroku.com/articles/heroku-cli"&gt;Heroku CLI&lt;/a&gt; (a.k.a Toolbelt) installed. Install using &lt;code&gt;npm install -g heroku-cli&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a href="#project-setup-command-line-work" id="project-setup-command-line-work"&gt;Project setup (Command line work)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Create a new directory &lt;code&gt;NodeRedDemo&lt;/code&gt; and change into it&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Initialize a new project &lt;code&gt;npm init&lt;/code&gt; - fill in suitable defaults&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Create a file &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; (content see below)&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;add NodeRED and the Salesfore nodes &lt;code&gt;npm install -s node-red node-red-contrib-salesforce&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;add a line into &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; (see sample below) in scripts: &lt;code&gt;"start": "node-red --settings ./.node-red/settings.js --userDir ./.node-red"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;create the directories &lt;code&gt;scripts&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.node-red&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;copy the &lt;code&gt;settings.js&lt;/code&gt; file from &lt;code&gt;node_modules/node-red&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;.node-red&lt;/code&gt; - We will edit that file later&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;initialize git: &lt;code&gt;git init&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;add initial files to git: &lt;code&gt;git add --all&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;git commit -m "initial creation"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;login to heroku &lt;code&gt;heroku login&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;add Heroku: &lt;code&gt;heroku create&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;deploy: &lt;code&gt;git push heroku master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Your application should be running on Heroku now. To learn how to use &lt;a href="http://nodered.org/"&gt;NodeRED&lt;/a&gt;, check out &lt;a href="https://nodered.org/docs/getting-started/first-flow"&gt;a tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. Besides running on Heroku you can start the application on local too. Just use &lt;code&gt;npm start&lt;/code&gt; and load localhost:1880.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;What is missing: protect your NodeRED editor, connect to Salesforce and of course: create your flows.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep in mind&lt;/strong&gt;: every time you redeploy or restart the app, anything stored, including your flow definitions, gets lost.&lt;br&gt; For permanent results I create my flows in the local instance of NodeRED and commit the flow file (in the .node-red directory) to git, so it becomes part of the deployment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2018/02/running-nodered-on-heroku-with-salesforce.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>d8031330-1131-11e8-a86d-4f29536bf933</guid>
	<pubDate>2018-02-14 03:42</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Excel in Continuous Integration</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Business Users like Excel. Besides its original use case of calculating, lists are a favourite use case. They also serve as poor man's requirement and bug tracker, so they siep into software development too.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;While Excel sheets are great for interaction, they are a beast for anything automation. The irony of it: Modern Excel files (the xslx flavour) are nothing less than &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Office_Open_XML"&gt;zip files with XML content&lt;/a&gt;. However that format is, let's say, [insert expletives here].&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;From an XML representation I would expect something like &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;cell row="23" col="44"&amp;gt;Some value&amp;lt;/cell&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. However that's not what Excel does. Rename an xlsx to zip and see for yourself. Also (which makes sense for Excel itself) empty cells are not represented in XML.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Cutting a long story short, an Excel file or its XML representation poses some challenges:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;XML format is not very suitable for automation, like generating reports using XSLT&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Excel automation only runs on Windows (and when you run headless, you trade the head for a headache). That makes it a no-go for most automation server environments&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Empty cells are absent from the XML (a variation of "not suitable")&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Cross reports with other files (e.g. logs in XML format) is hard&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;To overcome these limitations I wrote &lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/Excel2XML"&gt;Excel2XML&lt;/a&gt;. It is a little Java command line utility that converts Excel into a more digestible XML format. I used Microsoft's contribution to the &lt;a href="https://poi.apache.org/"&gt;Apache POI&lt;/a&gt; project to read the file. It has the following functions:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Extract workbooks in one or separate files per worksheet&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Ignore all formatting&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Computed cells return their last result values, unless it is a formula error, then the formula is returned&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;The first line of each sheet is treated as column headers, which are extracted as columns/column elements&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Each cell has a &lt;code&gt;column&lt;/code&gt;, a &lt;code&gt;row&lt;/code&gt; and a &lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt; attribute. The title reflects the value from the first row. This allows in XSLT to query the title instead of relying on the column number. Reordering, adding or removing columns won't kill your XSLT stylesheet that way&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Optional empty cells can be generated with an attribute of &lt;code&gt;empty="true"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Runs on Java8 completely from command line&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Calling it without parameters outputs the exact syntax of options&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The full syntax: &lt;code&gt;java -jar excel2xml.jar -i somefile.xslt [-o somefile.xml [ ]-e] [-s] [-w3,4]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;-i the input file in xslx format&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;-o the output file. If missing same name as input, but extension xml&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;-e generate empty cells. If missing: cells without data are skipped&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;-s generate a single file for the whole workbook. If missing: creates one file per sheet&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;-w comma separated list of sheets to export. Starts at 0. If missing: exports all sheets&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Head over to the git repository and grab &lt;a href="https://github.com/Stwissel/Excel2XML/releases"&gt;a release&lt;/a&gt;. Let me know what use you found. As usual YMMV&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2017/10/excel-in-ci.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H Wissel</author>
	<guid>8439A1CD09FAA0D2482581AD004F86B5</guid>
	<pubDate>2017-10-02 02:28</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Static APEX code analysis with PMD</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Coding standard are only as good as they are followed. One venerable tool to check source code is &lt;a href="https://pmd.github.io/"&gt;PMD&lt;/a&gt;. When you, like I did, wonder what acronym PMD represents, you will &lt;a href="https://pmd.github.io/pmd-5.8.1/overview/meaning.html"&gt;be disappointed&lt;/a&gt;. PMD supports the usual suspects like C, C++, C#, Fortran, Java, JavaScript, Go, Groovy, XML... as well as &lt;a href="https://pmd.github.io/pmd-5.8.1/pmd-apex/index.html"&gt;Apex&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://pmd.github.io/pmd-5.8.1/pmd-visualforce/index.html"&gt;Visualforce&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://pmd.sourceforge.net/snapshot/pmd-apex/rules/index.html"&gt;default ruleset for Apex&lt;/a&gt; contains 34 rules and are the ones also used by &lt;a href="https://codeclimate.com/"&gt;CodeClimate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;PMD is a Java application and you have a number options to run it:&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;ul&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;As a command line application&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Using ANT or Maven&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;In your CI platform (using command line, ANT or Maven &lt;img src="/blog/images/emoticons/wink.gif"&gt; )&lt;/li&gt; 
 &lt;li&gt;Linking your Github (or Gitlab, Bitbucket) repository to a service like &lt;a href="https://codeclimate.com/"&gt;CodeClimate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;PMD supports a series of output formats like plain, csv, html (different flavours) and XML. When you understand XSLT, the XML format allows you to render whatever report you deem fit&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2017/07/static-apex-code-analysis-with-pmd.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H Wissel</author>
	<guid>6535CE6D841F1A0048258168005D0105</guid>
	<pubDate>2017-07-25 04:55</pubDate>

</item>

</channel>
</rss>
