<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
	<title>wissel.net Usability - Productivity - Business - The web - Singapore and Twins</title>
	<link>https://wissel.net/blog/stories.rss</link>
	<description>Thoughts, Insights and Opinions of Stephan H. Wissel. Topics included: Salesforce, Lotus Notes and Domino, IBM Websphere, NodeJS, JavaScript,  J2EE, .Net, Software Archtecture, Personcentric Development, Agile Software, SDLC, Singapore and my Twins</description>
	<language>en,de</language>
	<copyright>(C) 2003 - 2021 Stephan H. Wissel, All rights reserved</copyright>
	<pubdate>Mon, 23 Feb 2026 15:30:01 +0000</pubdate>
<item>
	<title>VSCode launch settings for DominoJNX and HCL Notes 14.5</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;I'm not the only one who &lt;a href="https://youtu.be/d8WEzjDx4-E?si=ljSEAefAOKvrcrXr"&gt;doesn't like Windows&lt;/a&gt;, which is a problem when you depend on Domino Designer. Luckily there is Java and &lt;a href="https://opensource.hcltechsw.com/domino-jnx/"&gt;DominoJNX&lt;/a&gt;. A decade ago I would &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/39470027/running-an-ibm-notes-java-application-on-os-x-el-capitan-throws-unsatisfiedlinke"&gt;use Eclipse&lt;/a&gt; on an Intel Mac (and Java8). Much has changed. Java is now 21, the Mac is based on Arm and my primary IDE is &lt;a href="https://code.visualstudio.com/"&gt;VSCode&lt;/a&gt;. Here is my setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;x86 vs. arm&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run a Java app against the Notes 14.5 client there are several steps required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;An installed and running Notes 14.5 client (duh)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;MacOS Rosetta installed&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;a 64Bit x86 JDK (won't work with an ARM JDK)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;A &lt;code&gt;launch.json&lt;/code&gt; file in &lt;code&gt;.vscode&lt;/code&gt; of your project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
	<link>2026/02/vscode-launch-settings-for-dominojnx-and-hcl-notes.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>cc1e4050-011d-11f1-a041-fbe6b9e0116f</guid>
	<pubDate>04 February 2026</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Cumulative data modeling (Part 1)</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;The going approach to model data is drawing your &lt;a href="https://mermaid.ai/open-source/syntax/classDiagram.html"&gt;ER Diagram&lt;/a&gt; and map it to your persistence, be it &lt;a href="https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/dbms/normal-forms-in-dbms/"&gt;normalized&lt;/a&gt; in a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relational_database"&gt;RDBMS&lt;/a&gt; or an entry in a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NoSQL"&gt;NoSQL&lt;/a&gt; store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A slice of cake&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking through the use case of a cheese cake factory, slightly simplified. All process steps happen in batches, but batch sizes are not synchronized. E.g. dough mixing produces 0.8 - 1.4 times the baking capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/2026/CheeseCakeFactory.jpg" alt="Cheesecake factory"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corresponding data model would look like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/2026/CheeseModel800.png" alt="Cheesecake data model"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a customer wants to know if the slice is made with cheese from "happy cows", which is a trade certification some of the suppliers have. A simple SQL solves it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-sql"&gt;SELECT
    s.slice_id,
    ROUND(
        (SUM(CASE WHEN sup.HappyCowCertified = TRUE THEN mi.quantity_used ELSE 0 END) /
         SUM(mi.quantity_used)) * 100,
        2
    ) AS happy_cow_percentage
FROM Slices s
JOIN Baked_Cakes bc ON s.cake_id = bc.cake_id
JOIN Mix_Ingredients mi ON (
    mi.mix_id = bc.dough_mix_id OR
    mi.mix_id = bc.filling_mix_id OR
    mi.mix_id = bc.topping_mix_id
)
JOIN Ingredients i ON mi.ingredient_id = i.ingredient_id
JOIN Ingredient_Batches ib ON mi.batch_id = ib.batch_id
JOIN Suppliers sup ON ib.supplier_id = sup.supplier_id
WHERE s.slice_id = 'someSliceId'
  AND i.name = 'Cream Cheese'
GROUP BY s.slice_id;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another day another challenge: a batch from a supplier was sub standard and you need to recall all slices made with it. SQL to the rescue again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-sql"&gt;SELECT DISTINCT
    s.slice_id,
    s.storage_location
FROM Slices s
JOIN Baked_Cakes bc ON s.cake_id = bc.cake_id
JOIN Mix_Ingredients mi ON (
    mi.mix_id = bc.dough_mix_id OR
    mi.mix_id = bc.filling_mix_id OR
    mi.mix_id = bc.topping_mix_id
)
WHERE mi.batch_id = 'someBadBatchId'
ORDER BY s.slice_id;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as as bakery control system has this baked in (pun intended) or you have your residential SQL jockey on speed dial, all is well (keep in mind: the real data model is way more complex), but there might be a better way, slightly unconventional. Stay tuned for &lt;a href="#"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2026/01/cumulative-data-modeling-part1.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>557c13d0-f837-11f0-aa29-0b135a78174a</guid>
	<pubDate>23 January 2026</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Running your SPA on Cloudflare</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Your application is ready, you want to prepare for the incoming storm of users, so you separate your SPI server from your UI. To host the UI &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/"&gt;Cloudflare&lt;/a&gt; is chosen, while the API server sits in its data centre. There are a few steps to be had, which are simple, just the AI was acting cute, so I write it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/2026/CloudflareSPA.png" alt="Cloudflare hosted SPA"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Workers &amp;amp; Pages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We shall update our single page application whenever new contenet gets merged into &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;. All calls to &lt;code&gt;/api/*&lt;/code&gt; need to get routed to the API server. These are the steps that wrok. Nota bene: if you want to push from your local machine, the steps are different and a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;In Cloudflare head to &lt;code&gt;Build&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Compute &amp;amp; AI&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Workers &amp;amp; Pages&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Don't get distracted by the blue "Create application" button, you want to click above it and select &lt;code&gt;+ Add&lt;/code&gt; and then Pages (don't select "Worker")&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Select "Import an existing Git repository" and select your repo (You need the &lt;a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/integrations/cloud-and-saas/github/"&gt;GitHub integration&lt;/a&gt; for that).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;configure your build settings, for a &lt;a href="https://vite.dev/guide/"&gt;viteJS&lt;/a&gt; applicationa, the build command is &lt;code&gt;npm run build&lt;/code&gt; and the output directory is &lt;code&gt;dist&lt;/code&gt;. Save it and you are good to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next step is to configure "Custom domains", so &lt;code&gt;app.example.com&lt;/code&gt; points to your page. Follow the UI, it is almost automagic when Cloudflare is your DNS provider&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Redirecting &lt;code&gt;/api&lt;/code&gt; to the backend&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want Cloudflare to &lt;strong&gt;proxy&lt;/strong&gt; it, not to &lt;code&gt;30x&lt;/code&gt; redirect. A client wouldn't know that the request gets forwarded. This will allow to harden the API (e.g. drop all request not coming from Cloudflare) later on. Also you don't have to deal with &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Guides/CORS"&gt;CORS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search, with and without AI, suggested solutions revolving around files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;create &lt;code&gt;_routes.json&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;code &lt;code&gt;_worker.js&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;use an elaborate wrangler setups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those all have one thing in common: &lt;strong&gt;they didn't work&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What worked: create a folder &lt;code&gt;functions&lt;/code&gt; at the root of your repository. Inside add a file &lt;code&gt;[[path]].js&lt;/code&gt; - yes, that's two pairs of square brackets and th letters p a t h. It's the catch all for functions. Inside you add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-js"&gt;export async function onRequest(context) {
  const { request } = context;
  const url = new URL(request.url); // Test endpoint

  if (url.pathname === '/helloworld') {
    return new Response('Workers of the world unite!', {
      headers: { 'Content-Type': 'text/plain' }
    });
  } // Proxy API requests

  if (url.pathname.startsWith('/api/')) {
    url.hostname = 'api.example.com';
    url.port = '4443';
    url.protocol = 'https:';

    return fetch(url, request);
  }

  return context.next();
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of creating &lt;code&gt;functions/[[path]].js&lt;/code&gt;, create &lt;code&gt;functions/api/[[path]].js&lt;/code&gt; and simplify the function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-js"&gt;export async function onRequest(context) {
  const { request } = context;
  const url = new URL(request.url);

  url.hostname = 'api.example.com';
  url.port = '4443';
  url.protocol = 'https:';

  return fetch(url, request);
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardening the setup is a story for another time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual YMMV&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2026/01/running-your-spa-on-cloudflare.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>9d69e750-f62d-11f0-b02b-a7d7e8629bc5</guid>
	<pubDate>20 January 2026</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Unless you have a Google size API problem use curl</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;A few days ago &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/notessensei_api-curl-activity-7409921612931620864-uJXO"&gt;I posted on LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"&lt;em&gt;Unless you have a Google/Meta/Antropic size &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/API"&gt;API&lt;/a&gt; problem, I have a simple rule/insight:&lt;br&gt;
   Don?t create an api you can?t interact with using &lt;a href="https://curl.se/"&gt;curl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been asked to elaborate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The tool and the task&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly a remark about the tool, &lt;a href="https://curl.se/"&gt;curl&lt;/a&gt;. It is an incredibly powerful tool with super flexible use cases. Just look at the list of supported protocols: DICT, FILE, FTP, FTPS, GOPHER, GOPHERS, HTTP, HTTPS, IMAP, IMAPS, LDAP, LDAPS, MQTT, POP3, POP3S, RTMP, RTMPS, RTSP, SCP, SFTP, SMB, SMBS, SMTP, SMTPS, TELNET, TFTP, WS, WSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding, even mastering it, is a must have for any developer (or admin for that matter).Want to fetch data unencumbered by &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Guides/CORS"&gt;CORS&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Guides/CSP"&gt;CSP&lt;/a&gt; - curl is your friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the sentence above also this way: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don't design an API if you. haven't mastered curl&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picking an API architecture is a big decision and there are quite many to pick from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the markdown source code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;thead&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Architecture&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
   &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;/thead&gt;
 &lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer"&gt;REST&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Uses HTTP methods to access and change resources through URLs. Robust &lt;a href="https://www.openapis.org/"&gt;well supported&lt;/a&gt; architecture with mature tooling. Easy to discoverm used for Web services, mobile apps or public APIs. Not suitable for real-time bidirectional communication or data transfer minimalism. Typically uses JSON payloads, previously XML, but will cater any data. Complex queries need to be handled in application logic. Really needs &lt;a href="https://httpwg.org/http-extensions/draft-ietf-httpbis-safe-method-w-body.html"&gt;HTTP QUERY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Remote_procedure_call"&gt;RPC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;While REST is resource oriented, RPC is &lt;a href="https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/system-design/difference-between-rest-api-and-rpc-api/"&gt;action oriented&lt;/a&gt; and is not limited to the HTTP(s) protocol. Typically you have a single endpoint where the posted payload determines the action. Examples are &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOAP"&gt;SOAP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/JSON_Meta_Application_Protocol"&gt;JMAP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Object_Request_Broker_Architecture"&gt;CORBA&lt;/a&gt; or propriarty protcols like in use with &lt;a href="https://react.dev/reference/rsc/server-components"&gt;React Server Components&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://graphql.org/"&gt;GraphQL&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Client requests exactly the data it needs using a query language, used in apps needing flexible data fetching, reducing over-fetching. Since the Query is clientside complexity is shifted to the client and security can be a nightmare. Sucks for caching or file uploads. &lt;a href="https://developer.microsoft.com/en-us/graph/graph-explorer"&gt;Microsoft is a fan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOAP"&gt;SOAP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Simple Object Access Protocol)&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;XML-based protocol with strict standards and built-in error handling. Unparalled accurate through &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_Services_Description_Language"&gt;WSDL&lt;/a&gt; definitions. Works well between unrelated parties, e.g. &lt;a href="https://groups.oasis-open.org/communities/tc-community-home2?CommunityKey=eb27e05e-9bf5-4821-b1ed-018dc7d3f258"&gt;ebXML&lt;/a&gt;, heavy protocol, not popular in web applications anymore (despite giving &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ajax_(programming)"&gt;AJAX&lt;/a&gt; its name)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://grpc.io/"&gt;gRPC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Google Remote Procedure Call)&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;High-performance framework using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Protocol_Buffers"&gt;Protocol Buffers&lt;/a&gt;. The data definitions are not transfered, like in XML or JSON, so data transfer is minimized, can transfer bucket loads of data. When you run trillions of requests, like Google, every bit counts. Severe limitation on discoverability, language support and tooling. Best used server to server&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/WebSockets_API"&gt;WebSocket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Two-way communication channel over a single TCP connection used for Chat apps, live updates, real-time gaming, scaling is not for the faint of heart&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Webhook"&gt;Webhook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Server sends automatic HTTP callbacks when events occur. Basically two way REST. Elegant and hard to test unless you can control the callback destination. Popular for payment notifications, automated workflows, CI/CD pipelines. Has special needs to make it traceable, no guaranteed delivery or real-time two-way communication&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Message_queue"&gt;MQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Message Queue) or &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://mqtt.org/"&gt;MQTT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; (Message Queuing Telemetry Transport)&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Publish/subscribe messaging protocols, MQTT is suitable for low-bandwidth networks. Asynchronus processing of requests for loosely coupled systems. Very flexible but its store and forward principles require careful planning, especially around security and replay (keyword &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idempotence"&gt;Idempotency&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://kafka.apache.org/"&gt;Kafka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
   &lt;td&gt;Distributed streaming platform that handles high-volume data streams. In laymen's terms: a queue like MQ, with added transformation capabilities, persisten queue storage, suitable for really big volumes of data (just ask &lt;a href="https://www.uber.com/en-PH/blog/kafka-tiered-storage/"&gt;Uber&lt;/a&gt; about it). Fun to use, not fun to run (strongly advise &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=hosted+kafka"&gt;hosted Kafka&lt;/a&gt;). Kafka is the big gun, it can solve your problem, in a lot of case like a shipping container can deliver a single pizza&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the options (I'm sure there are more), you can see which ones can be covered by curl: REST, some RPC (when HTTP or SMTP based), GraphQL, SOAP, WebSocket, Webhooks (only to initialize). Eventually Kafka, when its http interface is active, but that's just http based RPC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compare the "Command Line Pain"? when using curl to model a request (or process the result with &lt;a href="https://jqlang.org/"&gt;jq&lt;/a&gt;). This gives you a data point you can add to your considerations which API to implement. It shouldn't be the only one: complexity, environment, data volumes, security etc. are equally important. The curl exercise helps to keep an eye on the tendency to overengineer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual YMMV&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2025/12/unless-you-have-a-google-size-api-problem-use-curl.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>ed2a6eb0-e618-11f0-8cc7-f32b674a3c60</guid>
	<pubDate>31 December 2025</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Higher Level Custom Events</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;A common occurence in web applications are button bars that execute various commands. So I was thinking of a pattern how to make this flexible and repeatable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Separate Event and Actions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical setup we find is like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-js"&gt;const btn = document.querySelector('#myButton');
btn.addEventListener('click', (event) =&amp;gt; {
  event.preventPropagation();
  // Business logic goes here
  doStuff();
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ties the logic to a low-level event of a low level component. To increase the usefulness we need to move from "mechanical" events to business level events, kind of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An anology: imagine a fastfood kitchen. The cook gets orders "2 burgers, large fries" that don't contain: customer tapped on the order kiosk, drive thru order or delivery request. This information iss handled by the front-desk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly we can approach the button event. Instead tying our business logic to the click event, we tie it to a higher level event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/blog/images/2025/ButtonEvents.jpg" alt="Components send events"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-js"&gt;const btn = document.querySelector('#myButton');
btn.addEventListener('click', (event) =&amp;gt; {
  window.dispatchEvent(new CustomEvent('update-request', { detail: { button: btn }, bubbles: true, composed: true }));
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is oblivious where the business logic happens, while the logic still knows where it came from by inspecting the detail object. Decoupling using custom events makes testing easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-js"&gt;window.addEventListener('update-request', updateStuff);
const updateStuff = async (event) =&amp;gt; {
  await doStuff;
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, so good. In the &lt;a href="#"&gt;next installment&lt;/a&gt; I'll tie it together with a custom component.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2025/11/higher-level-custom-events.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>979ef3a0-c087-11f0-abd4-772f20901b91</guid>
	<pubDate>13 November 2025</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>A flexible filter for collections or maps</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Building a proxy for http requests I came across an interesting generic problem: filter or mutate a map but only for the occurence of some given set of keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;That's a lot of &lt;code&gt;if - else - switch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The going approach is to have a specialized method with a switch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-java"&gt;  Map&amp;lt;String, String&amp;gt; transformMap(Map&amp;lt;String, String&amp;gt; input, String joker) {
    Map&amp;lt;String, String&amp;gt; result = new HashMap&amp;lt;&amp;gt;();

    input.entrySet().forEach(entry -&amp;gt; {
      String key = entry.getKey();
      String value = entry.getValue();
      switch (key) {
        case "a":
          result.put(key, "alpha");
          break;
        case "b":
          result.put(key, "beta");
          break;
        case "j":
          result.put(key, joker + "!");
        default:
          result.put(key, value);
      }
    });

    return result;
  }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gets big and hard to maintain fast, so I was thinking of a more neutral approach entertaining &lt;a href="https://docs.oracle.com/en/java/javase/21/docs/api/java.base/java/util/function/Function.html"&gt;Function&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://docs.oracle.com/en/java/javase/21/docs/api/java.base/java/util/Optional.html"&gt;Optional&lt;/a&gt;, hear me out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2025/10/a-flexible-filter-for-collections-or-maps.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>8e33a610-a13a-11f0-a492-855ef152a38b</guid>
	<pubDate>04 October 2025</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Arguing with Claude about StableCoins</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Winding down after a busy week, I decided to have som fun with &lt;a href="https://claude.ai/"&gt;Claude&lt;/a&gt;, so I &lt;a href="https://claude.ai/share/dd6f0e0d-1671-427e-ad4a-23239c3001ea"&gt;asked&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Explain to an A-Level student what stable coins are&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explain how they are created, distributed and backed. List the business model for coin issuers and traders. Discuss their advantages and risks compared to other cryptocurrencies as well as fiat currencies.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2025/09/arguing-with-claude-about-stablecoins.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>bbfd4e00-9a70-11f0-8765-1774fedaa2ba</guid>
	<pubDate>26 September 2025</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Authentication with PKCE and vanilla JavaScript</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Finally you got rid of user management in your application since your organisation has standardized on an &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/en-gb/learning/access-management/what-is-an-identity-provider/"&gt;IdP&lt;/a&gt;. There are plenty to choose from. I usually develop using a &lt;a href="/blog/2024/10/onetime-idp-with-keycloak.html"&gt;Keycloak&lt;/a&gt; IdP before I test it with the target IdP (and yes: Azure Entrada tries to be different).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it's time to adjust your &lt;a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/SPA"&gt;SPA&lt;/a&gt; to use the IdP. The admins tell you, you need to use &lt;a href="https://auth0.com/docs/get-started/authentication-and-authorization-flow/authorization-code-flow-with-pkce"&gt;PKCE&lt;/a&gt;, part of the &lt;a href="https://openid.net/developers/how-connect-works/"&gt;OIDC&lt;/a&gt; specification&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Where is the fun in ready made?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.npmjs.com/search?q=OIDC&amp;amp;sortBy=downloads_monthly"&gt;quick search on npmjs&lt;/a&gt; shows, the topic is popular and AWS takes the crown. But for deeper understanding, let's roll our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are just four items you need. The first three are provided by your IdP admins, the forth one you have to provide to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The URL of your IdP, the full path where &lt;code&gt;.well-known&lt;/code&gt; can be found. That's usually the root, but does differ for Entrada or Keycloak&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The issuer. That typically is the URL, except for Entrada&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The clientId. A String, usually opaque&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The callback urls. Pick those wisely. Typically you want three: &lt;code&gt;http://localhost:3000/myApp&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;https://localhost:8443/myApp&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;https://final.place.com/myApp&lt;/code&gt; The first two enable you to test your application locally with both http and https&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
	<link>2025/09/authentication-with-pkce-and-vanilla-javascript.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>d41aa310-8734-11f0-8a15-a76556d24dc9</guid>
	<pubDate>01 September 2025</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>Installing a macOS developer workstation</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;It is sitting on my desk, a shiny M4 MacBook. It wants to be configured. I can take the easy route and use the &lt;a href="https://support.apple.com/en-sg/102613"&gt;Migration Assistant&lt;/a&gt;. But that would carry forward all the cruft the various incarnations of the Migration Assistant have accumulated over the decade. So I went the hard way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Manual with a dash of AppStore&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First Stop: update macOS. In my case Sequoia 15.1 -&amp;gt; 15.6.1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installation falls into 3 categories&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;command line tooling&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;settings &amp;amp; data&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;GUI applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Followed by the reconfiguration of license keys&lt;/p&gt;</description>
	<link>2025/08/installing-a-macos-developer-workstation.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>ab012430-84d3-11f0-a69f-6fd5883f9ade</guid>
	<pubDate>29 August 2025</pubDate>

</item>
<item>
	<title>CouchDB, JWKS and PEM public keys</title>
	<description>&lt;p&gt;Depending on &lt;a href="/blog/2024/06/how-deep-do-you-authenticate.html"&gt;how deep you authenticate&lt;/a&gt;, you might be tasked maintaining a user base in &lt;code&gt;_users&lt;/code&gt; (and welcome to "I forgot my password" hell). The standing recommendation is to implement a single source of identity using a directory as &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/access-management/what-is-an-identity-provider"&gt;Identity Provider (IdP)&lt;/a&gt;. My favorite &lt;a href="https://couchdb.apache.org/"&gt;NoSQL database&lt;/a&gt; can be &lt;a href="https://docs.couchdb.org/en/stable/api/server/authn.html#jwt-authentication"&gt;configured&lt;/a&gt; to trust JWT signed by known IdPs, so let's do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some assembly required&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CouchDB can be configured in three ways: Edit the respective ini file, use the Fauxton UI or use the REST API. I like the later since I'm comfortable with &lt;a href="https://curl.se/"&gt;curl&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.usebruno.com/"&gt;Bruno&lt;/a&gt; (not a fan of Postman anymore). The steps are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;configure a client on your identity provider&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;enable JWT authentication&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;specify what claims are mandatory&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;specify how to map roles&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;add trustedd public keys&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;restart your node&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
	<link>2025/07/couchdb-and-jwks.html</link>
	<author>Stephan H. Wissel</author>
	<guid>268f01d0-6d46-11f0-802c-d975bb98b8ec</guid>
	<pubDate>30 July 2025</pubDate>

</item>

</channel>
</rss>
